# CHACKO BABU

Data Scientist with close to 8 years' experience working with data in diverse domains; corporate, academia, NGO and freelancing. Possesses demonstrable skills in areas of data sourcing, processing, conducting statistical analyses and communication of results.

chackobabun@gmail.com

chackobabu.github.io

🔻 #723, 1st A Cross Rd. Vijaya Bank Layout, Bengaluru, Karnataka

**+918086249788** 

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# **EUROMONITOR INTERNATIONAL** PBengaluru, Karnataka

#### **Data Analyst**

Feb 2024 - present

- Designed and implemented web-application to extract data from an internal database and user-friendly programs to enable seamless editing of the same, all through API calls. The process enhances data management efficiency and user experience within the organisation.
- Developed scripts to scrape webpages and parse information from PDFs.
- Designed and executed statistical models to forecast market sizes and project market share growth.
- Utilized SQL commands to extract data from BigQuery and MySQL tables.
- Leveraged the Linux CLI to administer tasks and operations on a virtual machine hosted within the Azure cloud environment.

#### Research Associate

Apr 2022 - Jan 2024

- Designed and implemented a system to automate the creation of Excel files, generating market-specific files at the onset of research and consolidating them afterward into a master file for analysis purposes.
- Performed thorough desk researches for in-depth market analysis.
- Crafted dynamic Tableau dashboards to visually illustrate evolving industry trends.

# 

#### Research Associate

Nov 2021 - Mar 2022

• Analysed data from factories' production floors for metrics such as line-efficiency, synchronization ratio etc, to identify areas for improvement.

## **DEPT. OF ECONOMICS AND SOCIAL SCIENCES, IIM-BANGALORE** ■ Bengaluru, Karnataka

#### Academic Associate

Aug 2018 - Jul 2021

- Extracted data from various public sources to build models and test various hypotheses in fields of international trade, migration, behavioural economics, financial economics etc using statistical and econometric methods.
- Worked as a Teaching Assistant; major courses handled were Advanced Microeconomics, Advanced Macroeconomics, Financial Economics.

# **CENTRE FOR DEVELOPMENT STUDIES** Thiruvananthapuram, Kerala

# Research Assistant

**i** Jul 2017 - Mar 2018

 Worked with multiple rounds of large-scale datasets of National Sample Survey for the study, along with other datasets such as KLEMS by RBI for various research projects.

# FREELANCE PROJECTS / CONSULTING ENGAGEMENTS

# **INDIA MIGRATION NOW ●** Remote

#### **Data Analyst (Freelance)**

**Sep** - Dec 2021

- Analyzed data on the NGO's daily operations and regularly updated a Tableau dashboard to visualize trends, enabling data-driven decision-making.
- Proactively addressed ad-hoc requests for data-wrangling and visualisations for reports and newsletters.

#### **NSRCEL, IIM-BANGALORE** ■ Bangalore, Karnataka

## **Data Science Project**

**Aug** - Sep 2021

 Analysed results of a primary survey on women entrepreneurs (participants of Goldman Sachs 10k Women program) for challenges they face in their entrepreneurship journey. The results of the analysis were communicated with actionable insights using visualisations and tables to stakeholders.

## **SKILLS**



# **EDUCATION**

**PowerShell** 

# **PG Diploma in Business Analytics**

Bash

**2**023 - ongoing

BITs Pilani - WILP

#### **MA Economics**

**2013-2015** 

Madras Christian College, Chennai

#### **BA Economics**

**=** 2010-2013

St Josephs College of Arts and Science, Bengaluru

# **AWARDS**

# National Eligibility for Lectureship in Economics

**Nov** 2017

University Grants Commission of India

# **LANGUAGES**

Malayalam
English
Hindi

# **INTERESTS**

I enjoy sketching, painting, reading novels, watching movies, studying history and politics, and cycling, among other hobbies.